Now when we think of our senses,
الآن عندما نفكر في حواسنا،
we don't usually think of the reasons
نحن لا نفكر عادة بالأسباب
why they probably evolved, from a biological perspective.
التي تطورت على الارجح من اجلها , من منظور بيولوجي.
We don't really think of the evolutionary need
نحن لا نفكر حقا بالحاجة التطورية
to be protected by our senses,
لنكون محميين بواسطة حواسنا ,
but that's probably why our senses really evolved --
ولكن هذا على الارجح السبب الذي جعل حواسنا تتطور حقا --
to keep us safe, to allow us to live.
للحفاظ على سلامتنا , بما يسمح لنا بالعيش.
Really when we think of our senses,
حقا عندما نفكر في حواسنا ,
or when we think of the loss of the sense,
أو عندما نفكر في فقدان الحاسة ,
we really think about something more like this:
نفكر عادة بشيء من هذا القبيل :
the ability to touch something luxurious, to taste something delicious,
القدرة على تلمس شيئ فاخر , تذوق شيء لذيذ ,
to smell something fragrant,
شم رائحة عطرة لشيء ,
to see something beautiful.
رؤية شيء جميل.
This is what we want out of our senses.
هذا هو ما نريده من حواسنا.
We want beauty; we don't just want function.
نريد الجمال , لا نريد الوظيفة فقط.
And when it comes to sensory restoration,
وعندما يتعلق الأمر باستعادة الحاسة ,
we're still very far away from being able to provide beauty.
نحن لا نزال بعيدين جدا عن أن نكون قادرين على تقديم الجمال.
And that's what I'd like to talk to you a little bit about today.
وهذا ما أود أن أتحدث إليكم قليلا عنه اليوم.
Likewise for hearing.
وبالمثل للسمع.
When we think about why we hear,
عندما نفكر لماذا نسمع,
we don't often think about the ability to hear an alarm or a siren,
نحن لا نفكر كثيرا بالقدرة على سماع صفارة إنذار أو جرس,
although clearly that's an important thing.
على الرغم من هذا أمر مهم للغاية.
Really what we want to hear is music.
ما نريد أن نسمعه حقا هو الموسيقى.
(Music)
(موسيقى)
So many of you know that that's Beethoven's Seventh Symphony.
الكثير منكم يعرف أن هذه هي السمفونية السابعة لبيتهوفن.
Many of you know that he was deaf, or near profoundly deaf,
الكثير منكم يعرف أنه كان أصما , أو أصم بالكامل,
when he wrote that.
عندما ألّف هذه المقطوعة.
Now I'd like to impress upon you
الآن أود أن أثير إعجابكم
how unusual it is that we can hear music.
كيف أنه من غير المعتاد أن نسمع الموسيقى.
Music is just one of the strangest things that there is.
الموسيقى هي واحدة من أغرب الأشياء الموجودة.
It's acoustic vibrations in the air,
إنها اهتزازات صوتية في الهواء ,
little waves of energy in the air that tickle our eardrum.
موجات صغيرة من الطاقة في الهواء تدغدغ طبلة أذننا.
Somehow in tickling our eardrum
بدغدغة طبلة أذننا بطريقة ما
that transmits energy down our hearing bones,
تنقل الطاقة نزولا عبر عظام السمع لدينا،
which get converted to a fluid impulse inside the cochlea
والتي يتم تحويلها إلى دفعة سائلة داخل قوقعة الأذن
and then somehow converted into an electrical signal in our auditory nerves
ومن ثم تحويلها بطريقة ما إلى إشارة كهربائية في الاعصاب السمعية لدينا
that somehow wind up in our brains
والتي تنتهي بطريقة ما في أدمغتنا
as a perception of a song or a beautiful piece of music.
كتصور لأغنية أو قطعة موسيقية جميلة.
That process is entirely abstract and very, very unusual.
هذه العملية تجريدية تماما وفي غاية السهولة.
And we could discuss that topic alone for days
ويمكن أن نناقش ذاك الموضوع لوحده لعدة أيام
to really try to figure out, how is it that we hear something that's emotional
في محاولة لمعرفة الحقيقة, وكيف أننا نسمع شيئا عاطفيا
from something that starts out as a vibration in the air?
من شيء على شكل اهتزاز في الهواء؟
Turns out that if you have hearing loss,
تبين أنه إذا كان لديك فقدان السمع ,
most people that lose their hearing
معظم الناس الذين يفقدون سمعهم
lose it at what's called the cochlea, the inner ear.
يفقدونه على مستوى ما يسمى بقوقعة الأذن، الأذن الداخية.
And it's at the hair cell level that they do this.
وهم يقومون بهذا على مستوى خليى الشعر.
Now if you had to pick a sense to lose,
الآن لو كان عليك اختيار حاسة لفقدانها،
I have to be very honest with you
يجب أن أكون صريحا جدا معكم
and say, we're better at restoring hearing
فأقول , نحن أكثر قدرة على استعادة السمع
than we are at restoring any sense that there is.
من أي حاسة أخرى موجودة.
In fact, nothing even actually comes close
في الواقع , لا شيء في الواقع يقترب حتى
to our ability to restore hearing.
من قدرتنا على استعادة السمع.
And as a physician and a surgeon, I can confidently tell my patients
وكطبيب وجراح , استطيع ان أخبر مرضاي بكل ثقة
that if you had to pick a sense to lose,
أنه إذا كان عليك اختيار حاسة لتفقدها،
we are the furthest along medically and surgically with hearing.
نحن أكثر خبرة طبيا وجراحيا مع السمع.
As a musician, I can tell you
كموسيقي , استطيع ان اقول لكم
that if I had to have a cochlear implant,
أنه إذا كان علي أن أخضع لزراعة قوقعة الأذن،
I'd be heartbroken. I'd just be plainly heartbroken,
سأكون حزينا. سأكون حزينا بوضوح،
because I know that music would never sound the same to me.
لأنني أعرف أن الموسيقى والصوت لن يبقى نفسه بالنسبة لي.
Now this is a video that I'm going to show you
الآن هذا هو الفيديو الذي سأعرضه عليكم
of a girl who's born deaf.
لفتاة ولدت وهي صماء.
She's in a very supportive environment.
انها في بيئة داعمة للغاية.
Her mother's doing everything she can.
والدتها تفعل كل ما تستطيع.
Okay, play that video please.
حسنا, شغل ذلك الفيديو من فضلك.
(Video) Mother: That's an owl.
(فيديو) الأم : تلك بومة.
Owl, yeah.
بومة , نعم.
Owl. Owl.
بومة. بومة.
Yeah.
نعم.
Baby. Baby.
رضيع. رضيع.
You want it?
تريدين ذلك؟
(Kiss)
(قبلة)
Charles Limb: Now despite everything going for this child
تشارلز ليم: الآن على الرغم من كل ما يحدث لهذه الطفلة
in terms of family support
من حيث دعم الأسرة
and simple infused learning,
والتعلم البسيط المقدم،
there is a limitation to what a child who's deaf, an infant who was born deaf,
هناك حد لما لطفل أصم، لرضيع ولد وهو أصم،
has in this world
في هذا العالم
in terms of social, educational, vocational opportunities.
من فرص اجتماعية وتعليمية ومهنية.
I'm not saying that they can't live a beautiful, wonderful life.
انا لا اقول انهم لا يستطيعون أن يعيشوا حياة جميلة ورائعة.
I'm saying that they're going to face obstacles
أنا أقول أنهم سيواجهون عقبات
that most people who have normal hearing will not have to face.
لن يواجهها معظم الناس الذين لديهم سمع عادي.
Now hearing loss and the treatment for hearing loss
الآن فقدان السمع وعلاج فقدان السمع
has really evolved in the past 200 years.
قد تطور حقا في ال 200 سنة الماضية.
I mean literally,
أعني حرفيا ,
they used to do things like stick ear-shaped objects onto your ears
كانوا يقومون بأشياء مثل وضع أجسام على شكل أذن داخل الأذن
and stick funnels in.
وإدخال قموع فيها.
And that was the best you could do for hearing loss.
وكان ذلك أفضل يمكن القيام به لفقدان السمع.
Back then you couldn't even look at the eardrum.
آنذاك لم يمكن ممكنا حتى النظر إلى طبلة الأذن.
So it's not too surprising
لذا فإنه ليس من المستغرب جدا
that there were no good treatments for hearing loss.
أنه لم تكن هناك علاجات جيدة لفقدان السمع.
And now today we have the modern multi-channel cochlear implant,
واليوم صارت لدينا عمليات زراعة قوقعة الأذن متعددة القنوات،
which is an outpatient procedure.
والتي هي عملية خارجية.
It's surgically placed inside the inner ear.
توضع جراحيا داخل الأذن الداخلية.
It takes about an hour and a half to two hours, depending on where it's done,
تستغرق حوالي الساعة والنصف إلى ساعتين، حسب مكان إجراءها،
under general anesthesia.
تحت تخدير عام.
And in the end, you achieve something like this
وفي النهاية , يجب تحقيق شيء من هذا القبيل
where an electrode array is inserted inside the cochlea.
حيث يتم إدخال نسق إلكترودي داخل القوقعة.
Now actually, this is quite crude
هذا في الواقع الآن في غاية الخشونة
in comparison to our regular inner ear.
بالمقارنة مع الأذن الداخلية العادية لدينا.
But here is that same girl who is implanted now.
لكن هذه الآن هي نفس الفتاة التي خضعت للزراعة.
This is her 10 years later.
هاته هي بعد عشر سنوات.
And this is a video that was taken
وهذا هو الفيديو الذي تم تصويره
by my surgical mentor, Dr. John Niparko, who implanted her.
من قبل مرشدي الجراحي , د. جون نيباركو، الذي أجرى لها الزراعة.
If we could play this video please.
قم بتشغيل الفيديو من فضلك.
(Video) John Niparko: So you've written two books?
(فيديو) جون نيباركو : إذن فقد ألفت كتابين؟
Girl: I have written two books. (Mother: Was the other one a book or a journal entry?)
فتاة : لقد ألفت كتابين. (الأم: هل كان الآخر كتابا أم تدوينا في اليوميات؟)
Girl: No, the other one was a book. (Mother: Oh, okay.)
الفتاة : لا, الآخر كان كتابا. (الأم : أوه , حسنا)
JN: Well this book has seven chapters,
ج.ن : حسنا هذا الكتاب من سبعة فصول,
and the last chapter
والفصل الأخير
is entitled "The Good Things About Being Deaf."
بعنوان : "أشياء جيدة عن كون المرء أصما".
Do you remember writing that chapter?
هل تتذكرين كتابة هذا الفصل؟
Girl: Yes I do. I remember writing every chapter.
الفتاة : نعم أفعل. أتذكر كتابة كل فصل.
JN: Yeah.
ج.ن : نعم.
Girl: Well sometimes my sister can be kind of annoying.
الفتاة : حسنا تكون أختي مزعجة نوعا ما أحيانا.
So it comes in handy to not be annoyed by her.
لذا فمن المفيد ألا أتعرض للإغاظة من طرفها.
JN: I see. And who is that?
ج.ن : أرى ذلك. ومن هو ذاك؟
Girl: Holly. (JN: Okay.)
الفتاة : هولي. (ج.ن : حسنا)
Mother: Her sister. (JN: Her sister.) Girl: My sister.
الأم : أختها. (يوحنا : أختها) الفتاة : أختي.
JN: And how can you avoid being annoyed by her?
ج.ن : وكيف يمكنك تجنب إزعاجها؟
Girl: I just take off my CI, and I don't hear anything.
الفتاة : أقوم فقط بإزالة القوقعة المزروعة، ولا أسمع شيئا
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
It comes in handy.
انها مفيدة.
JN: So you don't want to hear everything that's out there?
ج.ن : إذا كنت لا تريدين أن تسمعي كل ما هو في الخارج؟
Girl: No.
الفتاة : لا.
CL: And so she's phenomenal.
ت.ل : وبالتالي فهي استثنائية.
And there's no way that you can't look at that as an overwhelming success.
وليس هناك أي طريقة لا يمكن أن نرى بها هذا على أنه نجاح باهر.
It is. It's a huge success story in modern medicine.
هو كذلك. إنها قصة نجاح كبيرة في الطب الحديث.
However, despite this incredible facility
ومع ذلك , على الرغم من هذه السهولة المذهلة
that some cochlear implant users display with language,
التي يظهرها مستعملو القوقعة المزروعة في التعامل مع اللغة،
you turn on the radio and all of a sudden they can't hear music almost at all.
تقوم بتشغيل المذياع وفجأة لا يمكنهم سماع الموسيقى على الإطلاق.
In fact, most implant users really struggle
في الواقع , معظم من خضع للزراعة يعانون
and dislike music because it sounds so bad.
ويكرهون الموسيقى لأنها تبدو لهم سيئة جدا.
And so when it comes to this idea
وحتى عندما يتعلق الأمر بهذه الفكرة
of restoring beauty to somebody's life,
لاستعادة الجمال لحياة شخص ما,
we have a long way to go when it comes to audition.
أمامنا طريق طويل حين يتعلق الأمر بتجارب الأداء.
Now there are a lot of reasons for that.
الآن هناك الكثير من الأسباب لذلك.
I mentioned earlier the fact
لقد ذكرت في وقت سابق حقيقة
that music is a different capacity because it's abstract.
أن الموسيقى هي قدرة مختلفة لأنها مجردة.
Language is very different. Language is very precise.
اللغة مختلفة جدا. فاللغة دقيقة جدا.
In fact, the whole reason we use it
وفي الواقع, السبب الرئيسي الذي يجعلنا نستخدمها
is because it has semantic-specificity.
هي توفرها على خصوصياتها الدلالية.
When you say a word,
عندما تقول كلمة،
what you care is that word was perceived correctly.
ما يهمك هو أن تلك الكلمة تم فهمها بشكل صحيح.
You don't care that the word sounded pretty
لن تهتم إن كانت الكلمة تبدو جميلة
when it was spoken.
حين يتم نطقها.
Music is entirely different.
الموسيقى هي مختلفة تماما.
When you hear music, if it doesn't sound good, what's the point?
حين تسمع الموسيقى، إن لم تكن جيدة، فما الغرض منها؟
There's really very little point in listening to music
ليس هناك في الواقع غرض في الاستماع إلى الموسيقى
when it doesn't sound good to you.
حين لا يكون سماعها جيدا بالنسبة لك.
The acoustics of music are much harder than those of language.
صوتيات الموسيقى هي أصعب بكثير من نظيرتها في اللغة.
And you can see on this figure,
ويمكنكم أن تروا على هذا الرسم،
that the frequency range
أن نطاق التردد
and the decibel range, the dynamic range of music
ونطاق الدسيبل والنطاق الحيوي للموسيقى
is far more heterogeneous.
غير متجانس فيما بينها.
So if we had to design a perfect cochlear implant,
وبالتالي إن أردنا تصميم قوقعة أذن للزرع،
what we would try to do
ما قد نحاول القيام به
is target it to be able to allow music transmission.
هو استهدافه لجعله يسمح بتحويل الموسيقى.
Because I always view music as the pinnacle of hearing.
لأننا دائما أنظر إلى الموسيقى على أنها ذروة الاستماع.
If you can hear music,
إن كنت تستطيع سماع الموسيقى،
you should be able to hear anything.
يجب أن تكون قادرا على سماع أي شيء.
Now the problems begin first with pitch perception.
الآن تبدأ المشاكل أولا مع إدراك النغمة.
I mean, most of us know that pitch is a fundamental building block of music.
أقصد، معظمنا يعرف أن النغمة هي لبنة أساسية للموسيقى.
And without the ability to perceive pitch well,
وبدون القدرة على إدراك النغمة بشكل جيد،
music and melody is a very difficult thing to do --
الموسيقى واللحن هي شيء من الصعب جدا القيام به --
forget about a harmony and things like that.
لننسى التناغم وما إلى ذلك.
Now this is a MIDI arrangement of Rachmaninoff's Prelude.
الآن هذا هو ترتيب واجهة رقمية للآلات الموسيقية للمقدمة الموسيقية لراتشمانينوف.
Now if we could just play this.
الآن إن أمكن تشغيل هذا.
(Music)
(موسيقى)
Okay, now if we consider
حسنا , الآن إذا اعتبرنا
that in a cochlear implant patient
أنه في حالة مريض خضع لزراعة قوقعة الأذن
pitch perception could be off as much as two octaves,
قد يختلف إدراك النغمة بقدر مسافتين موسيقيتين،
let's see what happens here
دعونا نرى ما يحدث هنا
when we randomize this to within one semitone.
عندما كنا نرتب هذا بعشوائية على مستوى نصف نغمة.
We would be thrilled if we had one semitone pitch perception in cochlear implant users.
سنكون سعيدين إن كان لدينا إدراك نصف نغمي واحد في مستخدمي قوقعة الأذن المزروعة.
Go ahead and play this one.
أرجو أن تمضوا قدما وتشغلوا هذه.
(Music)
(موسيقى)
Now my goal in showing you that
الآن هدفي في عرض ذلك
is to show you that music is not robust to degradation.
هو أن تظهر لك أن الموسيقى ليست عصية على التدهور.
You distort it a little bit, especially in terms of pitch, and you've changed it.
تشوهها قليلا، ولا سيما فيما يتعلق بالنبرة، فتغيرها.
And it might be that you kind of like that.
وقد يحدث أن يعجبك ذلك.
That's kind of hypnotic.
ذلك تنويمي نوعا ما.
But it certainly wasn't the way the music was intended.
لكن ذلك بالتأكيد ليس المقصود من الموسيقى.
And you're not hearing the same thing
ولست تستمع إلى نفس الشيء
that most people who have normal hearing are hearing.
الذي يسمعه معظم ذوي السمع العادي.
Now the other issue comes with,
الآن المشكل الآخر يأتي مع،
not just the ability to tell pitches apart,
ليس فقط القدرة على التمييز بين النبرات،
but the ability to tell sounds apart.
ولكن القدرة على تمييز الأصوات عن بعضها البعض.
Most cochlear implant users cannot tell the difference between an instrument.
معظمي الذين خضعوا لزراعة القوقعة لا يستطيعون تحديد الفرق بين الأدوات الموسيقية.
If we could play these two sound clips in succession.
إن أمكن أن نشغل مقطعي الصوت هذين بالتتابع.
(Trumpet)
(بوق)
The trumpet.
البوق.
And the second one.
والثاني.
(Violin)
(الكمان)
That's a violin.
هذا كمان.
These have similar wave forms. They're both sustained instruments.
وهذه لديها أشكال موجية متشابهة. كلها أدوات مطردة.
Cochlear implant users cannot tell the difference
لا يمكن لمن خضع لزراعة القوقعة أن يعرف الفرق
between these instruments.
بين هاته الآلات الموسيقية.
The sound quality, or the sound of the sound
جودة الصوت، أو صوت الصوت
is how I like to describe timbre, tone color --
وهو ما يحلو لي أن أصف به طابع الصوت، ولون النبرة --
they cannot tell these things whatsoever.
لا يمكنهم التفريق بين هاته الأشياء أيا كانت.
This implant is not transmitting
لا تقوم القوقعة المرزوعة بنقل
the quality of music that usually provides things like warmth.
جودة الموسيقة التي توفر أشياء من قبيل الدفء.
Now if you look at the brain of an individual who has a cochlear implant
الآن لو نظرتم الى دماغ الشخص لديه قوقعة مزروعة
and you have them listen to speech,
وجعلته ينصت لخطاب،
have them listen to rhythm and have them listen to melody,
اجعلوه يستمع إلى إيقاع واجعلوه يستمع إلى لحن،
what you find is that the auditory cortex
ما تجده هو أن القشرة السمعية
is the most active during speech.
تكون الأكثر نشاطا خلال الخطاب.
You would think that because these implants are optimized for speech,
كنت أظن أنه ولأن هاته القوقعات المرزوعة هي الأمثل للكلام،
they were designed for speech.
تم تصميمها للكلام.
But actually if you look at melody,
ولكن في الواقع اذا نظرتم الى النغم،
what you find is that there's very little cortical activity
ما تجده هو أن هناك القليل جدا من الأنشطة القشرية
in implant users compared with normal hearing controls.
لدى من خضع للزراعة مقارنة مع أجهزة التحكم في السمع.
So for whatever reason,
وذلك لأي سبب كان،
this implant is not successfully stimulating auditory cortices
فهذه القوقعة المزروعة لا تحفز القشرات الصوتية بشكل ناجح
during melody perception.
خلال إدراك اللحن.
Now the next question is,
والسؤال التالي الآن هو،
well how does it really sound?
حسنا كيف يبدو حقا؟
Now we've been doing some studies
الآن قد قمنا ببعض الدراسات
to really get a sense of what sound quality is like for these implant users.
لمعرفة ماهية جودة الصوت لدى مستخدمي القوقعة المرزوعة.
I'm going to play you two clips of Usher,
سأشغل مقطعين ل آشر،
one which is normal
واحد اعتيادي
and one which has almost no high frequencies, almost no low frequencies
والآخر ليس فيه أي ترددات عالية أو متدنية تقريبا
and not even that many mid frequencies.
ولا حتى الشيء الكثير من الترددات المتوسطة.
Go ahead and play that.
قم بتشغيل ذلك.
(Music)
(موسيقى)
(Limited Frequency Music)
(موسيقى محدودة الترددات)
I had patients tell me that those sound the same.
كان لدي مرضى أخبروني أنها تبدو متشابهة.
They cannot differentiate sound quality differences
لا يمكن معرفة الاختلافات في جودة الصوت
between those two clips.
بين هذين المقطعين.
Again, we are very, very far away in just getting to where we want to get to.
مجددا، نحن بعيدون جدا من ناحية الوصول إلى حيث نريد.
Now the question comes to mind: Is there any hope?
والسؤال الذي يتبادر إلى الذهن: هل هناك أي أمل؟
And yes, there is hope.
أجل، هناك أمل.
Now I don't know if anybody knows who this is.
الآن لا أعرف إذا كان أي شخص يعرف من هو هذا.
This is ... does somebody know?
هذا هو... هل يعرفه أحدكم؟
This is Beethoven.
هذا هو بيتهوفن.
Now why would we know what Beethoven's skull looks like?
الآن لماذا نعرف ما تبدو عليه جمجمة بيتهوفن؟
Because his grave was exhumed.
لأنه تم نبش قبره.
And it turns out that his temporal bones were harvested when he died
واتضح أن تحصد عظامه الصدغية تم حصادها حين توفي
to try to look at the cause of his deafness,
في محاولة لإلقاء نظرة على سبب صممه،
which is why he has molding clay
وهذا هو سبب توفره على قالب طيني
and his skull is bulging out on the side there.
وجمجمته منتفخة خارجيا من الجانب هناك.
But Beethoven composed music
لكن بيتهوفن قد ألف الموسيقى
long after he lost his hearing.
بعد فترة طويلة من فقدانه للسمع.
What that suggests is that, even in the case of hearing loss,
ما يوحي به ذلك هو أنه، حتى في حالة فقدان السمع،
the capacity for music remains.
القدرة على تأليف الموسيقى لا تزال قائمة.
The brains remain hardwired for music.
لا تزال الأدمغة جاهزة لتلقي الموسيقى.
I've been very lucky to work with Dr. David Ryugo
لقد كنت محظوظا للغاية للعمل مع د. ديفيد ريوغو
where I've been working on deaf cats that are white
حيث أعمل على القطط الصماء التي هي بيضاء
and trying to figure out what happens when we give them cochlear implants.
وأحوال معرفة ما يحدث عندما نجري لها عملية زرع قوقعة الأذن.
This is a cat that's been trained to respond to a trumpet for food.
هذا قط تم تدريبه للاستجابة إلى بوق من أجل الطعام.
(Music)
(موسيقى)
Text: Beethoven doesn't excite her.
النص : بيتهوفن لا يثيرها.
The "1812 Overture" isn't worth waking for.
"افتتاحية 1812" لا تستحق الاستيقاظ من أجلها.
(Trumpet)
(بوق)
But she jumps to action when called to duty!
لكنها تقفز للحركة حين تدعى إلى الواجب!
CL: Now I'm not suggesting
ت.ل : الآن أنا لا أقترح
that the cat is hearing that trumpet the way we're hearing it.
أن هذا القط لا يسمع البوق بالطريقة التي نسمعه بها.
I'm suggesting that with training
مما يدل على أنه بالتدريب
you can imbue a musical sound with significance,
يمكنك إضفاء صبغة دلالية على صوت موسيقي،
even in a cat.
حتى لدى قط.
If we were to direct efforts
إذا كان لنا أن نوجه الجهود
towards training cochlear implant users to hear music --
نحو تدريب مستخدمي قوقعة الأذن للاستماع إلى الموسيقى --
because right now there's virtually no effort put towards that,
لأنه لم يتم بدل أي جهد عمليا للقيام بذلك،
no rehabilitative strategies,
لا وجود لاستراتيجيات إعادة التأهيل،
very little in the way of technological advances to actually improve music --
وهناك في الواقع القليل فقط من التطور التقني لتطوير الموسيقى --
we would come a long way.
كنا لنقطع شوطا طويلا.
Now I want to show you one last video.
الآن أريد أن أعرض لكم فيديو واحد الماضي.
And this is of a student of mine named Joseph
هذا طالب لدي يدعى جوزيف
who I had the good fortune to work with for three years in my lab.
والذي كنت محظوظا للعمل معه لثلاث سنوات في مختبري.
He's deaf, and he learned to play the piano
هو أصم، وتعلم العزف على البيانو
after he received the cochlear implant.
وقال أنه خضع لزراعة قوقعة
And here's a video of Joseph.
وهنا شريط فيديو لجوزيف.
(Music)
(موسيقى)
(Video) Joseph: I was born in 1986.
(فيديو) جوزيف : لقد ولدت سنة 1986.
And at about four months old,
وفي عمر الأربع أشهر تقريبا،
I was diagnosed with profoundly severe hearing loss.
تم تشخيصي بفقدان سمع حاد جدا.
Not long after,
لم يمض وقت طويل بعد ذلك،
I was fitted with hearing aids.
حين ركبت الأجهزة المساعدة للسمع.
But although these hearing aids
ولكن رغم أن هذه الأجهزة
were the most powerful hearing aids on the market at the time,
كانت مساعدات السمع الأقوى في السوق آنذاك،
they weren't very helpful.
لم تكن مفيدة للغاية.
So as a result, I had to rely on lip reading a lot,
نتيجة لذلك، اضطررت إلى الاعتماد على قراءة الشفاه كثيرا،
and I couldn't really hear what people were saying.
ولم أستطع فعلا أن أسمع ما يقوله الناس حقا.
When I was 12 years old,
عندما كان عمري 12 سنة،
I was one of the first few people in Singapore
كنت واحدا من الأوائل القلة في سنغافورة
who underwent cochlear implantation.
الذين خضعوا لزراعة القوقعة.
And not long after I got my cochlear implant,
وبعد فترة ليست بالطويلة حصلت على قوقعتي المزروعة،
I started learning how to play piano.
وبدأت أتعلم العزف على البيانو.
And it was absolutely wonderful.
وقد كان ذلك مذهلا بالفعل.
Since then, I've never looked back.
منذ ذلك الحين، لم ألتفت إلى الوراء.
CL: Joseph is phenomenal. He's brilliant.
ت.ل : جوزيف غير اعتيادي. إنه رائع.
He is now a medical student at Yale University,
وهو الآن طالب في كلية الطب في جامعة ييل،
and he's contemplating a surgical career --
وهو يفكر في مهنة الجراحة --
one of the first deaf individuals to consider a career in surgery.
واحد من أوائل الصم الذين يفكرون في دخول ميدان الجراحة.
There are almost no deaf surgeons anywhere.
لا تكاد تجد جراحين صم في أي مكان.
And this is really unheard of stuff, and this is all because of this technology.
وهذه أشياء غير مسموعة، وكل هذا بسبب هذه التقنية.
And the fact that he can play the piano like that
وحقيقة أنه يمكن العزف على البيانو هكذا
is a testament to his brain.
هي شهادة على دماغه.
Truth of the matter is you can play the piano without a cochlear implant,
في الحقيقة يمكنك أن تعزف على البيانو من دون زرع القوقعة،
because all you have to do is press the keys at the right time.
لأن كل ما عليك فعله هو الضغط على المفاتيح في الوقت المناسب.
You don't actually have to hear it.
ليس عليك فعلا الاستماع اليه.
I know he doesn't hear well, because I've heard him do Karaoke.
أعرف أنه لا يسمع جيدا، لأنني سمعته يؤدي كاريوكي.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And it's one of the most awful things --
وهو من أكثر الأشياء فظاعة --
heartwarming, but awful.
مثلج للصدر، لكنه فظيع.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And so there is certainly a lot of hope,
وبالتالي هناك بالتأكيد الكثير من الأمل،
but there's a lot more that needs to be done.
ولكن هناك الكثير جدا مما يجب القيام به.
So I just want to conclude with the following words.
لذلك أنا فقط أريد أن أختتم بالكلمات التالية.
When it comes to restoration of hearing,
عندما يتعلق الأمر باستعادة السمع،
we have certainly come a long way, a remarkably long way.
فنحن بالتأكيد قد قطعنا شوطا طويلا، شوطا طويلا بارزا.
And we have a much longer way to go
ولدينا شوط أكبر لنقطعه
when it comes to the idea of restoring perfect hearing.
عندما يتعلق الأمر فكرة استعادة السمع بشكل تام.
And let me tell you right now,
واسمحوا لي أن أقول لكم الآن،
it's fine that we would all be very happy with speech.
أنه من الجميل أن نكون جميعا سعداء للغاية مع الكلام.
But I tell you, if we lost our hearing,
لكني أقول لكم، إن فقدنا سمعنا،
if anyone here suddenly lost your hearing,
إن فقد أي شخص هنا سمعه،
you would want perfect hearing back.
سيريد استرجاع سمعه التام.
You wouldn't want decent hearing, you would want perfect hearing.
لن ترغب في سمع لائق، لكن ستريد سمعا تاما.
Restoration of basic sensory function is critical.
استعادة الوظيفة الحسية الأساسية أمر بالغ الأهمية.
And I don't mean to understate
وأنا لا أقصد أن أقلل
how important it is to restore basic function.
من أهمية استرجاع الوظيفة الأساسية.
But it's really restoration of the ability to perceive beauty
لكن الأمر يتعلق بفقدان القدرة على إدراك الجمال
where we can get inspiring.
حيث تتلقى الإلهام.
And I don't think that we should give up on beauty.
وأنا لا أعتقد أنه ينبغي لنا أن نتخلى عن الجمال.
And I want to thank you for your time.
وأريد أن أشكركم على وقتكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)